Guide to the California Physicians' Alliance Records, ca. 1988-1995
Department of Special Collections
California Physicians' Alliance Records,
ca. 1988-1995
Special Collections M0793
California Physicians' Alliance.
6 linear ft.
Stanford University. Libraries. Dept. of Special Collections and University Archives.
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
None.
Provenance
Gift of Bolerium Books, 1995.
Biography
The California Physicians' Alliance (CaPA) was started in May, 1987 as an organized group of physicians committed to the struggle for a single-payer health care plan, at both the state and federal level. The director of the group from 1987 to 1991 was Michael Pincus. He worked in conjunction with a council of presidents including Dr. Kevin Grumbach and Dr. Tom Bodenheimer. CaPA was a member-group of Health Access (HA) and Physicians for a National Health Program (PNHP) and worked closely with these organizations to further their cause of health care for all. Under the directorship of Mike Pincus, whose collected materials are the source of this collection, CaPA supported several health care bills. These included Bill No. 36 and Bill SB2686 by California Senator Nicholas Petris. CaPA was also responsible for writing the Right to Health Care Initiative which became Proposition 186. In addition, CaPA was in correspondence with many groups and individuals, including the Berkeley Gray Panthers and the Sacramento Central Labor Council of the AFL-CIO. Today, CaPA is largely merged with PNHP, although they maintain a separate identity in California. However, the group remains committed to working toward "...a national health program that guarantees one standard of comprehensive health care to all people."
Scope and Content
Correspondence, newsletters, minutes, agendas, and memoranda.
Access Terms
Bodenheimer, Thomas.; Grumbach, Kevin.; Margolin, Burt.; Petris, Nicholas.; Roberti, David.; Trachtenberg, Alan I.; AFL-CIO. Sacramento Central Labor Council.; Gray Panthers (Berkeley, Calif.).; Health Access.; Physicians for a National Health Program.; Health care reform.; Medical policy--United States.; Medicine--California
Container List
- Series I: California Physicians Alliance (CaPA)
  - Correspondence to CaPA members (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - First brochure / mailing (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Printed materials and flyers (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Meetings (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Speakers Bureau (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Malpractice Study Group (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - San Diego CaPA Chapter (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Newsletter #1-4 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Newsletter #5-8 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Newsletter #9- vol.2 no.3 (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Newsletter vol.2 no.4 - vol.4 no.3 (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - "The Thousand Recipe Chinese Cookbook" - notbook of Michael Pincus, executive director of CaPA (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - Right to Health Care Initiative (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - Correspondence from individuals 7/88 - 7/89 (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - Correspondence from individuals 8/89 - 2/90 (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - Correspondence from individuals 3/90 - 1/91 (Box 2, Folder 5)
  - Correspondence from groups 1986 - 1989 (Box 2, Folder 6)
  - Correspondence from groups 1990 - 1991 (Box 2, Folder 7)
- Series II: Health Access (HA)
  - Mission, Strategies, and Organization (Box 3, Folder 1)
  - Memoranda (Box 3, Folder 2)
  - Agendas for general meetings (Box 3, Folder 3)
  - Minutes for general meetings (Box 3, Folder 4)
  - Newsletters (Box 3, Folder 5)
  - Correspondence received (Box 3, Folder 6)
  - Correspondence to HA members and activists (Box 3, Folder 7)
  - Financial Statements (Box 3, Folder 8)
  - Steering Committee (Box 3, Folder 9)
  - Steering Committee Agendas (Box 3, Folder 10)
  - Steering Committee Minutes (Box 3, Folder 11)
  - Steering Committee Memoranda (Box 3, Folder 12)
  - Executive Committee and Conference Planning Committee Minutes (Box 4, Folder 1)
  - Health Access Initiative (Box 4, Folder 2)
- Series III: Physicians for a National Health Program (PNHP)
  - Mailings (Box 4, Folder 3)
  - Newsletters 1988 - 1989 (Box 4, Folder 4)
  - Newsletters 1990 (Box 4, Folder 5)
- Series IV: Groups Associated with CaPA
  - Voter Revolt (Box 4, Folder 6)
  - Community Health Coalition (Box 4, Folder 7)
  - Berkeley Gray Panthers (Box 4, Folder 8)
  - AFL - CIO (Box 4, Folder 9)
- Series V: Issues and Initiatives
  - Long Term Care (Box 4, Folder 10)
  - Universal Health Insurance (Box 5, Folder 1)
  - Catastrophic Health Insurance (Box 5, Folder 2)
  - Primary Care in Alameda County (Box 5, Folder 3)
  - Tobacco Tax and Health Protection Act (1988) (Box 5, Folder 4)
  - Alcohol Warning Bill (Box 5, Folder 5)
  - Mental Health Care Initiative (Box 5, Folder 6)
  - "Baby - Cal" (Box 5, Folder 7)
  - Gann Limit (Box 5, Folder 8)
- Series VI: Legislative Officials
  - California State Legislature (Box 5, Folder 9)
  - Petris - Bill No.36 (Box 5, Folder 10)
  - Petris - Bill SB2868 (Box 5, Folder 11)
  - Margolin (Box 5, Folder 12)
  - Roberti (Box 5, Folder 13)
- Series VII: Individuals Associated with CaPA
  - Grumbach, Kevin (Box 5, Folder 14)
  - Trachtenberg, Alan I. (Box 5, Folder 15)
  - Bodenheimer, Thomas (Box 5, Folder 16)
- Series VIII: Newsletters
  - Health System Reform (1990) (Box 5, Folder 17)
  - Health System Reform (1991) (Box 5, Folder 18)
  - Seniors in Sacramento (Box 6, Folder 1)
  - Health Care News (Box 6, Folder 2)
  - Northern California Medicine (Box 6, Folder 3)
  - State Health Notes (Box 6, Folder 4)
  - Miscellaneous newsletters (Box 6, Folder 5)
- Series IX: Articles
  - 1982-1989 (Box 6, Folder 6)
  - 1990-1991 (Box 6, Folder 7)
  - no date (Box 6, Folder 8)
- Series X: Miscellaneous
  - Correspondence (Box 6, Folder 9)
  - Printed Materials and Flyers (Box 6, Folder 10)
  - Bills and Initiatives (Box 6, Folder 11)